"How to Naturally Reduce
Wrinkles with Food"
After my video on dates
blew my mind, showing that
eating just a few dates
can significantly reduce
the duration of labor
during childbirth and
improve the progression of labor,
when I saw that there were
randomized controlled trials
showing that peanut balls
could decrease the length of labor,
I didn’t bat an eye, but no,
this is the peanut ball
they were talking about.
But there are some surprising
benefits attributed to nuts
in randomized controlled
trials, like how about a study
on the effects of almond
consumption on wrinkles?
Where’d they even
come up with the idea?
Well, population studies
have found that healthy diets
are associated with
less facial wrinkles,
like a meat and junk-
predominant eating pattern
was associated with
more wrinkles, whereas
a fruit-predominant pattern was
associated with fewer wrinkles.
In terms of single foods,
yellow vegetables and soy
appear protective, but
wine may make things worse.
Their thinking is that it
might be the antioxidants
in healthy foods decreasing
the oxidative stress load,
or the anti-inflammatory benefits,
or protection from sun damage,
or improved collagen production,
or better DNA repair.
I have videos on most
of those topics.
The bottom line is
that eating healthier
may reduce wrinkling, which
could actually save lives
if people started eating healthier
to maintain a more youthful
appearance and get all
the chronic disease benefits
as a happy side effect.
Other studies have found the same
thing, supporting recommendations
for more healthy foods like
fruits, vegetables, and nuts.
Here’s another
study that landed on
yellow vegetables,
and greens as well.
In this study, a high intake of
vegetables, beans, and olive oil
appeared to be protective against
spots of precancerous
sun damage,
whereas a high intake of meat
and dairy may make things worse.
Prunes, apples, and tea
seemed particularly good,
but this was a
cross-sectional study,
meaning just a snapshot in time.
Maybe people who eat more meat
are out barbequing in the sun,
or people who eat more prunes
just use more sunblock.
You can’t know for sure if
foods actually affect wrinkling
until you... put them to the test—
but we had no such
studies…until, now.
Why study almonds?
Because it was paid for by
the Almond Board, of course.
The researchers didn’t know
who was in the nut group, though,
and who was in
the control group,
until they were
looking at the results.
The nut group were given
2 ounces of nuts a day,
like two palmfuls of nuts, and
the control group was instead
given nut-free snacks
to eat instead
like nut-free granola
bars or pretzels.
Before and after, they got
high‐res facial photographs
to quantify facial wrinkle
depth and severity using
a computer‐based photographic
analysis and…boom,
the almond group had significantly
decreased wrinkle severity
compared with the control group
by the end of the 16-week study.
The paper concludes:
“Our study demonstrates that
daily almond consumption
may reduce wrinkle severity...”
Now, they used a relatively
large dose, 2 ounces a day,
whereas you can get
cardioprotective benefits
of nuts from even less
than a half an ounce;
so, who knows, maybe they could
have gotten away with using less.
Here’s the low-dose nut
study they referenced,
showing a significant drop in
LDL cholesterol within 6 weeks
eating just a few
almonds a day—10 grams
which is just like
8 almonds a day.
That’s the nice thing
about healthy foods,
they just have good
side effects.
So, global disease prevention
strategies might beneﬁt
from emphasizing that a
healthy diet is also linked
to less facial wrinkling,
and maybe vanity will help us
prevent a few heart
attacks in the bargain.